<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2012 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-usecases'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Use Case Diagrams and Flows</title>

 <section>
    <title>Portal Application Login</title>
    <para>
      Figure 1 illustrates a sample flow with a description of each request from the browser to the back end application.  This flow is taken from the "Gateway tutorial":http://resources.apexidentity.com/projects/docs/wiki/UseCase1 we encourage everyone take in order to learn how the Gateway works.  The Flat-File attribute store  will contain only one set of credentials and the Gateway makes the assumption this user is logging into the sample application.  In a real deployment the Gateway would look up the user credentials using its own session, a SAML2 assertion, or a header from an Access Management agent.  Please refer to the use cases below for examples of these types of deployments.
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/sso1.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>User accesses the Portal</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Gateway intercepts request, finds no login page and passes it through</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Portal finds no local session and redirects to its login page for authentication</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Gateway intercepts the redirect, finds a match for the login page, fetches 
          the credentials from the flat file
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Gateway creates the login form and POSTs it to the Portal login page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Portal validates the credentials and redirects to the user's home page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Gateway passes the request through to the browser.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
 </section>

 <section>
    <title>Access Management Integration</title>
    <para>
       Figure 2 illustrates the Gateway integrated into an Access Management deployment.  In this deployment the Gateway is running in a container which is protected by an Access Management agent. The agent is configured to forward a header, with the subject(user) of the single sign-on session, to the Gateway. The Gateway then uses the subject as the login credentials, or uses it as a reference to look up the login credentials in a database or directory.  The HR application is integrated into the SSO deployment without an agent or any modification to the application or its deployment configuration.
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/sso2.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
          <para>User browses to the Portal</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
           <para>Access Manager (AM) plugin intercepts the request, finds no 
            valid AM session,  redirects the user to the AM login pages</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
           <para>AM logs in the user and redirects back to the Portal</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
           <para>AM plugin finds a valid session, request goes through, the 
           Gateway passes the request through to the Portal</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
           <para>Portal finds no local session, redirects to  the Portal login page</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
           <para>Gateway inspects the redirect, finds a match for the login page, 
           creates the login form, and POSTs it to the Portal</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
           <para>Portal validates the credentials and redirects to the Portal page</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
           <para>Gateway passes the request through to the browser.</para>
       </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
 </section>
 
 <section>
    <title>Federation Gateway SP Initiated SAML2 SSO</title>
    <para>
      Figure 4 illustrates the Federation Gateway providing SAML2 endpoint features acting as Service Provider in an SP initiated single sign-on configuration.  In this sample, company myHR is an outsourced provider of HR services and has started seeing increased demand for SAML2 support in their core application. The companies to which they outsource are refusing proprietary means of Authentication and demanding the widely accepted SAML2 standard.  myHR is not in a position to modify their application to support SAML2 nor do they have the time or money to purchase, integrate, and deploy an Access Management solution.  With the  ApexIdentity Federation Gateway , myHR deploys the Gateway in front of their HR application, configure it as a SAML2 endpoint for SP initiated SSO,  and configure it to log users into the HR application upon successful verfication of the SAML2 assertion from their customers.
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/ssoFedSP.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
         <para>The user accesses the HR application through a bookmark in the browser</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>Federation Gateway inspects the request, no match is found for the 
         HR application's login page so the request goes through </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>HR application finds no HR session, sends a redirect to its login page</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>Federation Gateway intercepts the redirect, finds a match for the login 
         page, issues an SP initiated SSO SAML2 request to company.com's IDP</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>The IDP at Company.com receives the SAML2 AuthN and Authenticates the user</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>After authenticating the user the IDP sends a SAML2 POST to the Gateway</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>Federation Gateway validates the assertion and makes the assertion 
         attributes available to the Gateway login chain</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>The Gateway login chain gets the user credentials and  POSTs the login form to the application</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>The HR application verifies the credentials and redirects to its home page</para>
       </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
 </section>

 <section>
    <title>Federation Gateway IDP Initiated SAML2 SSO</title>
    <para>
      Figure 5 illustrates the Federation Gateway providing SAML2 endpoint 
      features acting as a Service Provider in a IDP initiated single sign-on configuration.
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/ssoFedIDP.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
          <para>User clicks the HR link on the company portal and is 
          redirected to the company IDP for authentication</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>IDP sends an AuthN Response to the HR application</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>Federation Gateway receives the POST, validates the assertion, 
          and makes the attributes available to the Gateway login chain</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>Gateway login chain retrieves the user credentials and 
          POSTs the login form to the myHR application</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>HR application validates the credentials and redirects to the main page of the application</para>
       </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
 </section>
 <section>
    <title>Standards Based SAML2 Agent</title>
    <para>
      Figure 6 illustrates the Federation Gateway as a standards based 
      replacement to proprietary Access Management Agents.
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/ssoFedAgent.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
         <para>The user accesses an internal Payroll application</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>Federation Gateway inspects the request, no match is found for the Payroll application's login page so the request goes through</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>Payroll application finds no Payroll session, sends a redirect to its login page</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>Federation Gateway intercepts the redirect, finds a match for the login page, issues an SP initiated SSO SAML2 request to company.com's Access Manager</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>Company.com's Access Manager receives the SAML2 AuthN and Authenticates the user</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>After authenticating the user the Access Manager sends a SAML2 POST to the Gateway</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>Federation Gateway validates the assertion and makes the assertion attributes available to the Gateway login chain</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>The Gateway login chain gets the user credentials and  POSTs the login form to the application</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>The Payroll application verifies the credentials and redirects to its home page</para>
       </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
 </section>

</chapter>

