<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2012 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-overview'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Solutions Overview</title>

 <para>ForgeRock's Open Identity Gateway (OpenIG) provides the answer to
 three important challenges.</para>

 <section xml:id="sso-for-any-app">
  <title>Extend SSO To Any Application</title>

  <para>In today's enterprise, more than 30% of web applications are
  incompatible with legacy web access management software. That is, unlike
  OpenAM with OpenIG, most web access management (WAM) products lack the agent
  to protect the web applications, or the application is a legacy solution that
  does not follow standard protocols for single sign-on. This limits the return
  on the enterprise WAM investment and constrains what types of web applications
  can be protected.</para>

  <para>ForgeRock's Open Identity Gateway addresses this problem by extending
  access management to encompass <emphasis>all</emphasis> web applications.
  With OpenIG, OpenAM deployments can now be extended to be inclusive of those
  applications that do not integrate with policy agents alone. In addition,
  ForgeRock Open Identity Gateway interoperates, out-of-the-box, with all
  management solutions. Most importantly, your organization can on-board any
  web application without ever modifying or touching the target application
  again, significantly reducing the development and quality assurance required
  to protect web applications.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="federate-any-app">
  <title>Federate Enabling Applications</title>

  <para>The expertise and cost required to add SAML2 support to web
  applications is a problem for many businesses. Those businesses not moving
  to a standard for exposing their applications to their customers see
  increased cost and maintenance due to the complexity of one-off proprietary
  integrations. They may also see a loss of business to those customers
  requiring a Federation standard for authentication. Sometimes, deploying all
  of OpenAM just to federate a few applications is too complex and costly, and
  building out their own solution by modifying their applications is just not
  possible.</para>

  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/federate-any-app.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <para>OpenIG lets you quickly federate any application.</para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>OpenIG Federation Gateway allows businesses to add SAML2 support to
  their applications with little to no knowledge of the standard. In addition,
  there is no need to modify the application or install any plugin or agent on
  the application container.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="standards-based-policy-enforcement">
  <title>Implement Standards Based Policy Enforcement</title>

  <para>In order to provide SSO, OpenAM policy enforcement points, the policy
  agents, have traditionally functioned as plugins for each application. The
  policy agents however use OpenAM specific APIs and protocols. In contrast,
  you can roll out OpenIG as an independent policy enforcement point that is
  built on the SAML2 standard.</para>

  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/standards-based-agent.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <para>OpenIG integrates well as a policy enforcement point with OpenAM and
    with other standards based solutions.</para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>OpenIG Federation Gateway can replace policy agents with a standards
  based SAML2 compliant enforcement point.</para>
 </section>
</chapter>
