<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2014 ForgeRock AS
  !
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-oauth-rs'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                             http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Configuring ${projectName} as an OAuth 2.0 Resource Server</title>

 <para>
  This chapter explains how ${projectName} acts as an OAuth 2.0 Resource Server,
  and follows with a tutorial
  that shows you how to use ${projectName} as a resource server.
 </para>

 <indexterm>
  <primary>OAuth 2.0</primary>
  <secondary>Resource server</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 <section xml:id="about-oauth2-rs">
  <title>About ${projectName} as an OAuth 2.0 Resource Server</title>

  <para>
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6749"
   >The OAuth 2.0 Authorization Framework</link> describes a way of
   allowing a third-party application to access a user's resources
   without having the user's credentials.
   When resources are protected with OAuth 2.0,
   users can use their credentials with an OAuth 2.0-compliant identity provider,
   such as OpenAM, Facebook, Google and others
   to access the resources, rather than setting up an account
   with yet another third-party application.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <para>
    In OAuth 2.0, there are four entities involved.
   </para>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <firstterm>resource owner</firstterm> is the end user
     who owns protected resources on a resource server.
    </para>

    <para>
     For example, a resource owner has photos stored in a web service.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <firstterm>resource server</firstterm> provides
     the user's protected resources to authorized client applications.
    </para>

    <para>
     In OAuth 2.0, an authorization server grants the client application
     authorization based on the resource owner's consent.
    </para>

    <para>
     For example, a web service holds user's photos.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <firstterm>client</firstterm> is the application
     that needs access to the protected resources.
    </para>

    <para>
     For example, a photo printing service needs access to the user's photos.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <firstterm>authorization server</firstterm> is the service
     responsible for authenticating resource owners and obtaining their consent
     to allow client applications to access their resources.
    </para>

    <para>
     For example, OpenAM can act as the OAuth 2.0 authorization server
     to authenticate resource owners and obtain their consent.
     Other services can play this role as well.
     Google and Facebook for example provide OAuth 2.0 authorization services.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   In OAuth 2.0, there are different grant mechanisms
   whereby the client can obtain authorization.
   One grant mechanism involves the client redirecting the resource owner's browser
   to the authorization server to complete authentication and authorization.
   You might have experienced this grant mechanism yourself
   when logging in with your identity provider account to access a web service,
   rather than creating a new account directly with the web service.
   Whatever the grant mechanism,
   the client's aim is to get an
   OAuth 2.0 <firstterm>access token</firstterm> from the authorization server.
  </para>

  <para>
   Access tokens are the credentials used to access protected resources.
   An access token is just a string that represents the authorization
   to access protected resources given by the authorization server.
   An access token, like cash, is a bearer token.
   This means that anyone who has the access token can use it to get the resources.
   Access tokens therefore must be protected,
   so requests involving them must go over HTTPS.
   The advantage of access tokens over passwords or other credentials
   is that access tokens can be granted and revoked
   without exposing the user's credentials.
  </para>

  <para>
   When the client requests access to protected resources,
   it supplies the access token to the resource server housing the resources.
   The resource server must then validate the access token.
   If the access token is found to be valid,
   then the resource server can let the client have access to the resources.
  </para>

  <para>
   When ${projectName} acts therefore as an OAuth 2.0 resource server,
   its role is to validate access tokens.
   How an access token is validated is technically not covered
   in the specifications for OAuth 2.0.
   Typically the resource server validates an access token
   by submitting the token to a token information endpoint.
   The token information endpoint typically returns
   the access token, when it expires,
   and the OAuth 2.0 <firstterm>scopes</firstterm> associated with the token,
   potentially with other information.
   In OAuth 2.0, the token scopes are strings
   that can identify the scope of access authorized to the client,
   but can also be used for other purposes.
   For example, OpenAM maps them to user profile attribute values by default,
   and also allows custom scope handling plugins.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the tutorial that follows,
   you configure ${projectName} as a resource server,
   and use OpenAM as the OAuth 2.0 authorization server.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="oauth2-rs-tutorial-before-you-start">
  <title>Preparing the Tutorial</title>

  <para>
   In the chapter on
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="gateway-guide#chap-quickstart"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
   ><citetitle>Getting Started</citetitle></link>,
   you learned how to configure ${projectName}
   to proxy traffic and capture request and response data.
   You also learned how to configure ${projectName}
   to use a static request to log in with hard-coded credentials.
  </para>

  <para>
   This tutorial shows you how ${projectName}
   can act as an OAuth 2.0 resource server,
   validating OAuth 2.0 access tokens and including token info in the exchange.
  </para>

  <para>
   This tutorial relies on OpenAM as an OAuth 2.0 authorization server.
   As an OAuth 2.0 client of OpenAM, you get an access token.
   You then submit the access token to ${projectName},
   and ${projectName} acts as the resource server.
  </para>

  <para>
   Before you start this tutorial,
   prepare ${projectName} and the minimal HTTP server as you did for the chapter on
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="gateway-guide#chap-quickstart"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
   ><citetitle>Getting Started</citetitle></link>.
  </para>

  <para>
   ${projectName} should be running in Jetty,
   configured to access the minimal HTTP server as described in that chapter.
  </para>

  <para>
   The initial ${projectName} configuration file should look like the one used
   to login with a hard-coded username and password, see
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="gateway-guide#config-login-static-request"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
   ><citetitle>Configuration for Hard-Coded Credentials</citetitle></link>.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <para>
    If you get stuck running the following samples,
    know that you can activate ${projectName} debug logging
    with a "ConsoleLogSink" configuration object.
    Add it as the first object in the array of configuration objects.
   </para>

   <programlisting language="javascript">
{
    "name": "LogSink",
    "type": "ConsoleLogSink",
    "config": {
        "level": "DEBUG"
    }
}
   </programlisting>
  </tip>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="oauth2-rs-tutorial-openam-config">
  <title>Setting Up OpenAM as an Authorization Server</title>

  <para>
   Install and configure OpenAM on
   <literal>http://openam.example.com:8088/openam</literal>
   with the default configuration.
   If you use a different configuration,
   make sure you substitute in the tutorial accordingly.
   Although this tutorial does not use HTTPS,
   you must use HTTPS to protect access tokens in production environments.
  </para>

  <para>
   Login to the OpenAM console as administrator,
   and use the common task wizard, Configure OAuth2,
   to configure an OAuth 2.0 authorization server in / (Top Level Realm).
  </para>

  <para>
   Also create an OAuth 2.0 Client profile in / (Top Level Realm).
   This allows you to request an OAuth 2.0 access token on behalf of the client.
   In OpenAM console, browse to
   Access Control > / (Top Level Realm) > Agents > OAuth 2.0 Client,
   and then click New in the Agent table.
  </para>

  <para>
   Create an OAuth 2.0 client profile with name <literal>${projectName}</literal>
   and password <literal>password</literal>.
   The name is the OAuth 2.0 client_id, and the password is the client_secret.
  </para>

  <para>
   Edit the <literal>${projectName}</literal> client profile
   to add <literal>mail</literal> and <literal>employeenumber</literal> scopes
   to the Scope(s) list, and then save your work.
   In this tutorial,
   you overload these profile settings to pass credentials to ${projectName}.
   This tutorial uses <literal>mail</literal>
   and <literal>employeenumber</literal>
   for the sake of simplicity.
   Both of those attributes are part of a user's profile
   out of the box with the default OpenAM configuration.
   Neither of the attributes are needed for anything else in this tutorial.
   So this tutorial uses <literal>mail</literal> to hold the username,
   and <literal>employeenumber</literal> to hold the password.
   In a real deployment, you would no doubt use other attributes
   that depend on how the real user profiles are configured.
  </para>

  <para>
   Finally, edit the OpenAM demo user to set credentials in
   the Email Address and Employee Number fields of the demo user profile.
   In OpenAM console, browse to the user profile under
   Access Control > / (Top Level Realm) > Subjects > User > demo.
   Set Email Address to <literal>george</literal>
   and Employee Number to <literal>costanza</literal>.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="oauth2-rs-tutorial-gateway-config">
  <title>Configuring ${projectName} as a Resource Server</title>

  <para>
   To configure ${projectName} as an OAuth 2.0 resource server, you use an
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="reference#OAuth2ResourceServerFilter"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
   >OAuth2ResourceServerFilter</link>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The filter expects an OAuth 2.0 access token
   in an incoming <literal>Authorization</literal> request header,
   such as the following.
  </para>

  <programlisting language="http">
Authorization: Bearer 7af41ddd-47a4-40dc-b530-a9aa9f7ceda9
  </programlisting>

  <para>
   The filter then uses the access token to validate the token
   and to retrieve token information from the authorization server.
   On successful validation, the filter injects
   the response from the authorization server into
   <literal>exchange.oauth2AccessToken</literal>.
  </para>

  <para>
   If no access token is present in the request,
   or token validation does not complete successfully,
   the filter returns an HTTP error status to the user-agent,
   and ${projectName} does not continue processing the exchange.
   This is done as specified in the RFC,
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6750"
   >OAuth 2.0 Bearer Token Usage</link>.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can therefore add additional filters and handlers to the chain
   directly after the <literal>OAuth2ResourceServerFilter</literal>,
   and expect to have the access token if the filter completes successfully.
  </para>

  <para>
   To configure ${projectName} as an OAuth 2.0 resource server,
   replace the <filename>config.json</filename> file
   with the new configuration from the example,
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="gateway-guide#config-oauth2-rs"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
   ><citetitle>Configuration for an OAuth 2.0 Resource Server</citetitle></link>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Notice "ResourceServer" configuration.
   This configuration includes
   a client handler to send access token validation requests,
   the list of required scopes that the filter expects to find in access tokens,
   the OpenAM token info endpoint used to validate access tokens,
   and <literal>"enforceHttps": false</literal> to allow testing
   without having to set up keys and certificates.
   (In production environments, do use HTTPS to protect access tokens.)
  </para>

  <para>
   When the "ResourceServer" filter
   has injected information for a valid access token into the exchange,
   the "CaptureTokenInfo" filter dumps the token information to the log.
   The "CaptureTokenInfo" filter also injects the credentials
   from the user profile in OpenAM into the exchange.
  </para>

  <para>
   Finally, the "LoginRequestFilter" logs a user in to the minimal HTTP server
   by using the credentials injected from the token information.
   In this simple configuration, all requests result in login attempts
   against the minimal HTTP server.
  </para>

  <para>
   After updating <filename>config.json</filename>,
   restart Jetty server so that ${projectName} loads the new configuration.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="oauth2-rs-tutorial-test">
  <title>Trying It Out</title>

  <para>
   To try your configuration, you need an access token.
   Get an access token from OpenAM and use it to access ${projectName}
   as in the following example,
   which uses the OAuth 2.0 resource owner password credentials authorization grant.
  </para>

  <screen>
$ <userinput>curl \
 --user "${projectName}:password" \
 --data "grant_type=password&amp;username=demo&amp;password=changeit&amp;scope=mail%20employeenumber" \
 http://openam.example.com:8088/openam/oauth2/access_token</userinput>
<computeroutput>{
    "scope": "mail employeenumber",
    "expires_in": 600,
    "token_type": "Bearer",
    "refresh_token": "7fe9b284-698e-4738-ad11-01b984920861",
    "access_token": "b8102957-486b-47f2-bd2b-54faa55ec363"
}</computeroutput>

$ <userinput>curl \
 --header "Authorization: Bearer b8102957-486b-47f2-bd2b-54faa55ec363" \
 http://www.example.com:8080</userinput>
<computeroutput>...<![CDATA[
    <h1>User Information</h1>

    <dl>
        <dt>Username</dt>
        <dd>george</dd>
    </dl>

    <h1>Request Information</h1>

    <dl>
        <dt>Method</dt>
        <dd>POST</dd>

        <dt>URI</dt>
        <dd>/</dd>

        <dt>Headers</dt>
        <dd style="font-family: monospace; font-size: small;">...</dd>
    </dl>
]]></computeroutput>
  </screen>

  <para>
   Also look in the Jetty server output to see the raw token information.
   The raw token information looks something like the following.
  </para>

  <programlisting language="none">
2014-08-04T16:43:38Z:CaptureTokenInfo.CaptureTokenInfo:INFO:
{
    "access_token": "b8102957-486b-47f2-bd2b-54faa55ec363",
    "mail": "george",
    "employeenumber": "costanza",
    "grant_type": "password",
    "scope": [
        "mail",
        "employeenumber"
    ],
    "realm": "/",
    "token_type": "Bearer",
    "expires_in": 35
}
  </programlisting>

  <para>
   What is happening behind the scenes?
  </para>

  <para>
   After ${projectName} gets the <command>curl</command> request,
   the resource server filter validates the access token with OpenAM,
   and injects the token information into the exchange.
   (If the access token was missing or invalid,
   then the resource server filter would have
   returned an error status to the user-agent.
   The OAuth 2.0 client would then have had to deal with the error.)
  </para>

  <para>
   The "CaptureTokenInfo" filter logs the token information,
   and also extracts the credentials to inject them into the exchange.
   Finally the login filter uses the credentials to log the user in
   to the minimal HTTP server,
   which responds with the User Information page.
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
